There's no way to convince a vegan to
have bacon and extra breakfast and vice
versa. There's other things obviously we
work with US foods large kind of
actually food delivery food service is
truck drivers their concept of a lunch
is McDonald's
>> we can't tell them oh here's the list go
shop whole food so airone and [laughter]
then go home and cook at homes it's like
okay McDonald's it is we're going to
reverse your diabetes on McDonald's diet
and by the way we do that
>> okay I don't want that to get buried
>> what are some sample meals that people
might get out of McDonald's or something
like Uh,
I will start I suppose with something
that I can potentially use immediately
or some variant thereof. Do you still
schedule your week or at least workouts
each Sunday? And I'm reading here, this
is from a blog post. Schedule
everything. This is top five tips
getting and staying in shape for people
who are busy. I spend 10 to 20 minutes
every Sunday scheduling most of my
workouts in details similar to any other
appointments in my calendar. Like with
most unscheduled tasks and to-dos,
they'll fall between the cracks. On the
other hand, with proper scheduling,
you've managed to get in your workouts
with 150 plus annual travel days,
changing cities, super early wakeups and
delayed flights, etc. So, this is kind
of a micro question that edges into the
macro just around planning and
scheduling, but do you still take time
out each Sunday to go through these
things?
>> 100%. 100%. It's every Sunday. I just
find that structure allows flexibility
and spontaneity.
>> If you don't have structure, nothing
gets done. At least in my life. And not
that my life is super special, but you
know, two pretty young kids, happily
married, running a company, growing
that's dozen employees, and then trying
to be a kind of semi athlete in the
process. If I don't schedule, it's not
going to happen. So, I I spend about 15
minutes at the end of each week that
Sunday.
>> Mhm.
>> Professionally, kind of list the three
things that absolutely have to get done,
and then I schedule a few things,
including workouts, and it works very
well. When do you do that on Sunday?
>> Well, this could be a longer
conversation, but it's either early
morning before the kids wake up and kind
of Sunday gets going or if I don't have
it done by Sunday afternoon, then it's
after 7:00 p.m. when everybody else kind
of quiets down and
>> Mhm.
>> I take my own time.
>> How many employees? Could you remind me,
Verta, how many employees do you have
right now?
>> Yeah, Vert Health. So, we we're about
thousand employees. And the caveat these
days of course is don't brag about
employees cuz the more employees you
have less you leverage AI but I guess
mentioning thousand employees it's a
real company and obviously growing fast
so it it takes fair amount of effort so
about thousand people. Well, the good
news is like so many companies in the
news these days, if you did end up
overhiring during COVID or something,
you can not say we made a mistake. You
can just say we're using AI to improve
efficiency [laughter] when you have
layoffs,
but we won't dwell on that. The question
I had is what type of training in your
life right now are you currently
scheduling each week?
>> Good question. Well, we're talking about
training. So this is sort of physical
training.
>> Physical training
>> is really in two buckets. The primary
focus is is really endurance sports
around cycling.
>> So I do a lot of mountain bike racing as
well as road bike racing. So that's
essentially endurance training. So I'd
say 90% is is cycling related and that's
my core workout that essentially happens
in the morning every day. 99% of the
time it's one of the first things. It's
not the very very first thing in the
morning. So that's one. We can go into
morning routines and stuff like that in
a second if that's interesting. But I do
a little bit of just sort of core work
pretty much first thing after waking up.
So I don't even have to schedule that.
That's sort of a non-negotiable before
the brain even boots up. I've done my
kind of core work. But cardiovascular
work is the main. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Let's not tease. Let's just hop
right into it. So what what does the
morning look like upon waking up? And
what time are you getting up?
>> Okay, let's separate into traveling and
not traveling. Traveling for work and
not traveling. Let's do non-traveling.
>> Yeah, non-traveling.
>> I wake up 5:00 a.m. latest. This morning
alarm was 4:45. So I wake up pretty
early. And I have the amazing privilege
and luxury that the second I roll off
the bed, I jump into a lake.
>> Mhm.
>> Or pond. And you know, it's not a long
time, maybe like a minute, just cold
water. Couple of strokes, but it's
essentially it's like a freezing cold
shower. And this is a mountain lake, so
we're talking like 40°
>> Mhm. [snorts]
>> weather pretty much straight off the
bed. And after that, maybe just like a
minute or two of some air squats and
jumps and core, literally core work,
nothing too special. So that's like some
supermans and leg raises and stuff like
that. And I do it because again, I raise
bicycles quite a bit and I have some
lower back issues and core work. It just
never gets done unless it's the very
very first thing in in the morning. And
then I'll throw in a couple of push-ups
there. So it's it's you know that's 5 to
10 minutes straight off the bed jump
into the lake tripping wet little bit
core a little bit jumps a little bit
this and that and I'm just a huge not
just a believer but the practical
experience I've had is kind of mood
follows movement emotion so before I
even ruminate or think anything I've
already been in a lake and done five or
10 minutes of core work and some jumping
and get the heart rate up for a little
Mhm.
>> And that's pretty much the first 5 10
minutes. And then the other thing I I
try to do always right after is do
something useful for other people. Do
something useful for other people. And
what is that in practice when I'm not
traveling? It's preparing coffee for my
wife
>> and emptying the dishwasher. It may
sounds very simple, but that's like 15
minutes after I've woken up. I haven't
had a second to think about or ruminate,
oh my back's hurting, or oh my god, so
much work or whatever that is.
>> It's like a 15minute sort of boot up
sequence
>> and it's like life's rocking and then
kind of I'm ready to go and and do the
other things. Don't worry, I won't have
you give the minuteby minute for your
entire day. But after you have done
that, so you've made made coffee for
your wife, you've emptied the
dishwasher,
then what are you having your first
intake of coffee, what does the next
kind of 30 to 60 minutes look like for
you,
>> man? Sounds like a mind readader. So, I
do drink coffee, so that's time for an
espresso or cup of coffee at that point.
and that everybody else is still
sleeping in the house. I sit down and
basically I write down kind of my sleep,
how many hours I slept and I kind of
have a little diary. It's a spreadsheet
online,
>> 16 years of data now. And I also write
three things I'm grateful for. So this
kind of little gratitude journal, super
super simple things. And I try to focus
on the mundane such as you know leaves
in the aspen trees or warm temperature.
It's just simple things very very simple
things. So I do that and write down a
few things and then I usually work for
about an hour. So like clean email and
slacks or maybe I have like a 20 minute
writing thing. So this is kind of my CEO
job. So I try to do about hour of that
and then whenever my wife wakes up then
we have sort of a 15 20 minute couples
moment drink coffee and talk about life.
It's a really wonderful moment there. So
that's kind of the very morning and then
my real workout usually happens between
sort of 6:30 and 8:30 [clears throat]
exercise.
>> Got it.
>> And then after that get to office.
exception would be if I have any
meetings that are across time zones,
then could be a 6 a.m. Zoom or something
like that. But before that, I've always
done my swimming in a lake and a little
bit core and maybe a cup of espresso.
That's the routine. And pretty much
repeated that for more than a decade.
And there's nothing too special. I
always say people ask like what's the
science behind I say, listen, if it
doesn't feel good, it's not right for
you. If it feels good, repeat it.
>> [laughter]
>> So, I mean, I suppose there are
different types of fun, right? There's
type one, type two, maybe type three
fun, which is God, I can't remember who
sent this to me.
It was a friend of mine. Maybe you
recall who this is because I'm sure I
pinged you about it, but they were
driving up some windy, incredibly steep
road in the mountains and they were
taking a video from their car of some
lunatic who I think they call a lunatic.
Like, look at this [__] guy. He's
crazy on what you could envision
listeners or watchers as incredibly long
rollerblades. They're basically skis
with a single track of wheels on them
and poles doing uphill, I suppose,
Nordic skating, let's just call it going
up this unending
incline. And they're like, "God, who
[clears throat] is that lunatic?" And of
course, who did it end up being ended up
being Sami, right? [laughter] So fun
means different things or feeling good
means different things in different
contexts. But the reason for people who
are wondering why am I digging all into
all these details. Number one, I like
the details and the details matter. But
you have always impressed me with the
number of important pillars that you're
able to methodically schedule into your
life and furthermore within those
pillars how you're able to operate at a
very high level in multiple domains. So
that's why I'm asking about the
specifics because
these things much like workouts tend not
to happen accidentally
>> if you don't schedule them particularly
with the number of moving pieces that
you have and frankly the number of
moving pieces that any person probably
has things will not manifest magically.
And I'm curious we talked about the
single day. Do you have any type of I
know for training you almost certainly
do have like weekly and monthly
architectures particularly with
competitions but from a work could be
work could be physical perspective do
you have a consistent weekly
architecture of any type where say you
might batch certain types of tasks or
meetings or otherwise on certain days or
anything like that or is it pretty much
Monday to Friday more or less the same
daily routine? I do have a system.
[laughter]
Well, a couple of things. First, kind of
I think it's good to remind myself for
anyone's like, "Oh, here's the system."
And the reality is life happens all the
time. So, let let's just remember that
you're running a company, you have kids,
crap hits the fan all the time or at
least frequently. So, obviously, you
have to be flexible. So, what I'm going
to share next is the kind of beautiful
clean scenario where you can kind of
live with your structure. But the
reality is you're running a company.
>> The platonic ideal gets smashed.
>> Yeah. Exactly. A lot.
>> It's 24/7 and the Sunday afternoon walk
with your kids or or your spouse may not
happen cuz you need to address the
crisis. But you mentioned like, oh, I'm
kind of impressed how how many things
you can do.
Honestly, the biggest secret is saying
no to 99%
of the things that many people consider
quoteunquote normal. So what you care
gets done. And sometimes people ask me
like, "Wow, it's so many sacrifices. You
trying to be an athlete and a CEO and a
founder and trying to be a parent as
well and you even travel with your kids.
Like you must have so many sacrifices."
I actually find that saying no is
incredibly liberating in life. I'm way
happier that I'm married to one person
versus five. It's awesome. There's no
way I could be a CEO of many companies.
I I love the kind of focus.
And so I actually find it personally in
life when you find something that kind
of fills your cup and is satisfying and
gratifying, just having the one or two
things that I focus on and then go all
in rather than a sacrifice. It's like a
happy place for me. So anyway, so I
would say that's my biggest secret. I
think a lot of people will hear what
you're saying and theoretically agree
with it and yet most people are unable
to embrace that in practice, right? For
whatever reason and doesn't mean they're
not capable of doing it, but they don't
do it. Why do you think people have
trouble
saying no or the default is people are
inclined to overcommit or that they do
the 99% of things that are quote unquote
normal that you say no to? Why do you
think not more people do what you're
describing?
>> Honestly, if I had a perfect answer, I'd
probably write a book about it
>> with all your spare time.
>> Here's my guess. I think one might just
be a narrative. I can't tell you how
many times someone has said, "Oh my, you
must be sacrificing so much to be able
to do what you do." And I'm sure you
could say the same for an Olympic
athlete. Like, "Oh my god, so many
sacrifices." But if you're an Olympic
athlete, focus on your sport and your
craft.
Sure, you can't do 99% of things quote
unquote normal people do, but it's
probably incredibly satisfying to be
able to do that one thing for the five
or 10 or 15 years of your life. So
that's why I meant so maybe it's a
narrative that oh if if I say no to all
these whatever that is movie night every
night or some distraction whatever
staying on social media and watching
Netflix for hours a day that oh it's a
sacrifice not to do that. So that's my
guess one thing that's a narrative in
our minds like oh you want to do all
these consumption things that maybe take
time away from the thing that could move
your life or profession forward. So, so
that could be one. And then the other
thing is I think this sort of life
structure that if you don't have a
basic,
we can go back to your original question
that what's kind of your architecture
and what's your structure. If you've
never taken the time to take a step back
and say, "Hey, how am I allocating my
time?" [clears throat]
>> Mhm. It's very easy to let the universe
or the entropy to kind of take control
of of your time, whether that's your
inbox or text messages from others or
phone calls. It's actually very very
easy. Let the world run your life as
opposed to you running your life.
>> Well, let's talk about the weekly
architecture and then I am going to come
back to this particular
question that I asked. But let's let's
take a breather on that and would love
to hear more about the weekly
architecture or other architectures
outside of the daily.
>> So again, this is sort of in an optimal
world, but I would say professionally I
do try to group similar type of tasks
into specific days. So just to give you
an example, Monday is filled with a lot
of kind of group and leadership meetings
and stuff like that. So there's one kind
of context switching that it's meetings
in front of the whole company and in
front of leadership team and so forth.
So so that's Monday. Tuesday I try to
have all my one ones again one type of
context switching and as an introvert
that takes a lot of energy by the way as
important it is and sometimes very
enjoyable but the kind of one person
after another it's pretty draining for
me personally. How many direct reports
do you have?
>> Well, I should say this has changed all
the time.
>> Yeah,
>> there's been 15, there's been 10, and I
had eight for a long time, but for the
last couple of months, I've had two.
>> Only two, which is a very small number.
And again, [clears throat] that could be
another 1 hour conversation. But when
you're building a grow company,
you always have to ask yourself what's
most important for this year. And
there's not really kind of a school book
perfect
>> kind of approach. But anyways, he's two
right now. So Tuesday is that Wednesday
I actually try to reserve for thinking
and writing thinking and writing. So the
default is no meetings.
>> Mhm.
>> And one example of writing that I do I
write a team letter for the whole
company from the CEO. So I've now
written 553
of
>> Wow. So you do that every week? every
week and there's like a one topic and
again another topic we could dive into
but what I find is that it's as the
company has scaled there are a few
things that are very scalable like
whether my email hits five inboxes or
thousand obviously doesn't take any time
away from me but I can give context
explain what's happening what's
important what's happening in outside
world what's happening inside the
company and then every employee feels
hopefully some level of connection
that's one example there's couple of
things that I've kind of repeated ever
since day one and now at thousand
employee scale still very scalable but
that's just one example it could be
preparing for board meeting or thinking
about strategy which sounds very
high-flying but I I would say one thing
that's very very easy
as a CEO of a grow company is to fool
yourself that you're productive and
useful by being busy
>> Mhm. But if you miss a decision,
something around a corner, no amount of
knocking tasks off the to-do list is
going to compensate that.
[clears throat]
>> Mhm.
>> And it's almost like managing your own
brain and feelings.
It's hard not to have a tightly
scheduled calendar, but in fact having
that time open for like you can go for a
walk and think about the problem. So
anyways, that's kind of my Wednesday.
And then Thursday and Fridays is a lot
of internal client work and those kinds
of things. But I usually that's not too
structured. But that's that's a little
bit of a typical week.
>> On Wednesday, when you're doing the
writing and thinking, what are some of
the ways that you structure your
thinking? There's unstructured thinking.
You can go for a walk and kind of ponder
and allow the void to invite hopefully
some type of insight. But then there's
structured thinking. And I guess to the
extent that I know you at all, I would
say I'm inclined to think you probably
have some prompts or structure or an
approach to doing thinking. What does
that look like or how would you speak to
that?
>> Typically, the way my brain works is the
actual thinking and problem solving
happens 24/7. And I'll give you a
specific example. my workouts every
morning which is is about an hour hour
and a half unless it's a very very very
high intensity that's one of the best
times where my thinking happens and sort
of problem solving and new ideas and
creativity happens there and then for
the Wednesday I actually just block like
an hour and say it's almost like the
time to get the words and the thoughts
and whatever that might be off my brain
to a paper or obviously in the cloud. So
unless I have to do a very kind of
leftbrain mathematical
deterministic problem solving thing like
literally like okay let's look at how do
we improve crush margin orism like that
>> the creative work does not happen at the
desk
>> for me
>> and I'll give you one thing that I
noticed this was especially during co
when covid hit I was listening a lot of
podcasts and music and audio books on
100% of my workouts was maybe like a
here
and I realized that the problem solving
and the creativity almost like stopped.
So now I have a rule that maximum of
half of my workout I can listen to Tim
Ferris. [laughter]
I said sorry. So if your download
numbers are going down or or listen
[laughter] numbers,
>> damn it, Sammy, I need all the help I
can get. [snorts]
>> So if the brain is in a consumption
mode, you're kind of just filling the
cup. And I I've noticed the creative
thoughts and the problem solving that's
happening kind of in a background
processing is is not happening. So
anyways, that's a tactical thing that
I've noticed that too much audio book uh
podcasts kind of filling the brain and
it stops creating stuff. It's it's very
interesting. That's at least my personal
experience. So I'm very conscious of on
those moments when I'm you know
exercising or walking or driving
somewhere that there's kind of like a
cut off point. No more listening. Just
let your brain do its thing. And then
the Wednesday comes in. It's more like,
okay, now I kind of have the framework
in my head, take an hour and a half to I
don't know, write about next year's
priorities. So this going to the new
product we're going to launch and or
even these team letters that I write. I
actually write them in my brain when I'm
away from the desk and then when I sit
down, it just it comes up.
>> That actually leads into my follow-up
question. And I can't imagine I'm the
only person wondering this, which is
when you're doing these workouts, let's
just say it's an hour and a half to two
hours, the real workouts, right, in the
morning. I would imagine quite a lot
percolates and comes up and if you're
doing that Monday, Tuesday, maybe also
Saturday, Sunday, etc. By the time you
get to Wednesday, if I have not taken
some step to maybe verbally record some
of that or make short notes in a
notebook for cues for later, I would be
doubtful that I would be able to recall
the good ideas that I had earlier in the
week. Do you just have a pre-ternatural
sort of inclination to be able to
remember all that stuff or do you take
some type of shortorthhand
after the workouts so that you can use
those then on Wednesday as prompts? How
does that work?
>> Essentially, I write emails to myself
>> or store notes. It's the same thing. So
there's tidbits along the week and then
I have it
>> for Wednesday and [clears throat] then
you know half maybe in the in the brain
and half is written somewhere so I don't
forget it all
>> and you just send yourself an email
after the workout with some type of
note.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> What is an example of what you might
cover in a team company email on a
Wednesday and how long is that? That is
like you mentioned earlier one of the
things you've repeated since day one.
What would be an example that you can
share? I mean it could be hypothetical
but just like what might you put into
that and how long is it?
>> Half is standard structure. So there's a
quote from again we can go into details
but you know we're in a business of
reversing metabolic disease and helping
people get healthy with nutrition. So we
treat patients like real humans hundreds
of thousands. So half of it is just
existing structure. There's a quote from
a patient. So we always kind of lead
with this is why we're here and here's
kind of a positive feedback from a
patient. Then there's some business
metrics like how much we've grown and
what are the priorities and just a
reminder of this year's kind of key
objectives. And so half is like that and
then the most important other half is
topic of the week. So topic of the week
is essentially my as a CEO founder essay
and I think that's what you were asking.
I would say they're rling in two or
three categories. One is what has
happened in external world. What's the
context there and how does that affect
us? You know, one example, this is a
real world example that I' I've written
quite a bit about since we use nutrition
as the core tool,
but obviously our providers use all the
tools in a toolkit. One of the things
that has really changed in addressing
obesity and metabolic disease over the
last couple of years is the GLP-1 drugs.
So these are the ompics of the world.
And so I've had number of letters
discussing how do these drugs
potentially affect how we take care of
our patients and what's the impact on
our business. So that would be
externality and how is that affecting
our strategy. So that's one example. The
other category is career and personal
advice to our team members like how to
make most out of your experience working
at Verta and around that kind of stuff
that we discussed we've discussed now
like personal productivity and how do
you make most out of so that's I would
say is is the second category
and then third is just internal this is
what happened this is what it means for
us so honestly it's I kind of like it
it's my personal outlet and sometimes um
said, "Hey, 530 plus
essays. There's a book in the making.
All we need to do is upload it to Chat
TPT and we have a book ready to be
published." [laughter]
>> So, I I promised I would come back to a
thread, which I realized is probably a
misworded question. And the question I
asked was
why people have trouble doing what you
do, which is saying no to 99% of the
things that that normals do or feel
compelled to do. To your point about the
narrative and I and I realize that's
perhaps not the right question. the the
the right question might be what advice
would you give to someone who is having
trouble saying no or focusing on just a
few things but I can make it much more
specific because I think the more we can
imagine it uh perhaps the the easier it
is to dig into this so let's say that
you had a relatively new hire right who
is on the younger side but you know a
10x engineer or some equivalent of that
someone who is clearly a superstar but
who has not established the type of
architecture
and routine that you have in your life.
And let's just say you sense that they
are on the path to burnout, which is
going to be bad for them. It's going to
be bad for the company. It's going to be
bad for the patients you serve.
>> And and you want to stage an
intervention to help them
correct course. I imagine you may have
even had these conversations. What might
that conversation or coaching look like?
>> Well, funny enough, this has been one of
the topics of my team letters, one of
the 530. [laughter]
So, I would separate it into two things.
My my advice, one would be this sort of
planning. I literally it would be very
simple. sit down for five minutes on a
on a Sunday evening before the week
starts and write down what absolutely
completely needs to get done next week.
Super duper simple, professionally or
personally, and schedule it into your
calendar like literally. And if you have
the flexibility, then like block two
hours in the mornings to get those two
or three things done. And then when life
happens or work happens, everything else
kind of comes after that. So that to me
would be the number one thing. And then
I would couple that when Monday comes or
Tuesday comes, it's, you know, whether
you work in an office or in a remote
setting, do not let the universe
control your time. So this means
absolutely no notifications.
Maybe if you have to get text message
for I don't know family emergency or
something but like take everything else
out and you kind of create that sacred
space where you can do that work whether
that's writing or coding or calling 15
cold calling 15 prospects or whatever
that is. It's it's super duper simple
but it's so easy to then sort of again
Monday comes Tuesday comes and then the
world takes over and you're like oh my
god it's 4 p.m. I haven't done the
thing.
>> So I'd say that would be the one
category.
>> Can I pause for one second?
>> Yeah sure. Okay. So, before we get to
the second, for some people listening,
if if they were sit down for 10 minutes
on Sunday to write down the things that
must get done
professionally and personally, they
might have a list of 20 things in each
category.
So, are we talking about one thing,
three things in each category? I know
this seems like very
personnicity, but this seems like a
possible failure point for people,
right?
>> Yeah. So what is your suggestion there?
>> So it's probably one or two things but
this again we could launch into another
part which is obviously you need an
architecture of annual thinking
planning.
>> Sure.
>> What is the business need for example in
fact I just have a text file as file on
on my computer here's the four things to
remember as a CEO now and 20 years from
now. Here's the three things for this
year and here's the three things for
this week. I literally have a text file
and I just update it every Sunday. And a
whole another topic which I'm sure some
people think I'm crazy is I have a
15-year plan for myself which I kind of
accidentally stumbled that it actually
could be useful and I updated every year
and again we can take that offline or
take a bookmark how that came about.
It's been incredibly helpful. And again,
I want to highlight structure allows
spontaneity and flexibility. But if you
don't have that architecture, then
obviously on a Sunday evening, it's
like, oh, should I write a book or get a
new job or just do this project that my
boss was asking? So, it's like if you
don't have that north star, you could be
kind of spinning like a compass. Yeah.
Run a magnet. I did take you off track
because you were saying block these
things out in the calendar like Sunday 5
to 10 minutes.
>> Block those things out in your calendar
if you can. 2 hours first thing in the
morning. Do not let the universe
>> dictate how you use your time. Block out
notifications. And then you said the
second thing and then that's when I
interrupted you. Second bucket. This is
probably the most important as it
relates kind of like a burnout and you
just kind of you're falling apart and
I'm going to knock here on my wood my
table. Not too hard to create any any
noise. But I founded my first software
company in April 2000. So now it's we're
here in 2026. So that's 26 years running
building fast growth companies. And I I
haven't cracked yet. And again, caveat
is it could happen tonight. So but
there's a few things I've learned. I
think these are applicable to especially
any knowledge worker where kind of like
everything's just coming to your brain
and it's it's very easy to you know get
stressed and anxious and cracked and I
written about this as well. Here's my
formula that has worked for me very
well. One you have to take care of your
sort of foundational metabolic health.
What is it? It's sleep, nutrition,
exercise. So that's kind of one. If you
are metabolically very very unhealthy
it's very very likely that you're going
to crack under pressure. So that's one.
Second one is it's very helpful to have
especially for kind of founder CEO types
but for anyone have at least two or
three identities or outlets. For me it's
parent husband one CEO two and then
wannabe athlete. And so if one's
failing, hopefully at least two other
are the areas outlets in my life where
it's like a it's going okay. And by the
way, it's never that I'm rocking and
winning and ringing the bell in all
three at the same time. And it's very
helpful. It's it's almost like a Jedi
mental trick like, "Oh my god, work
sucks, but at least my kids love me
today." [laughter] So, so having that
outlet and particularly founder types,
younger ones, it's often the opposite
that they're sort of proud of the fact
that I only have one thing and I'm ready
and willing to die for my company. Well,
that's all well and good when
everything's going well, but you have
the first kind of speed bump and then
everything falls apart. So, that's the
second thing I would say. Third one is
have peers outside of your company that
you can kind of let your hair down.
Sorry, sorry that I know. let your head
down and relax. For me, it's a group of
CEOs. Other CEOs was, "Oh my god, can
you believe? Can you believe this
employees are bitching again?"
Obviously, you can't say that in front
of the company. Personally, for me, it's
been YPO, the young president's
organization since I guess 2008. So, now
it's for me, it's not anymore the why
the young, it's just PO. I'm [laughter]
old enough. So, I have that. And then
the fourth one I would say is you know
everyone has their own tools but just
understanding how your mind work. It
could be meditation, could be some other
tools but that's been a process for
myself to just realize that if you are
just attached to your thoughts
eventually they're going to get you and
you can't really think yourself out of
the hole that you thought yourself into.
So unless you can take a step back and
kind of like observe like oh my god my
brain's having a life of its own. So
that's kind of the toolkit I would not
to crack. So foundational health have
different outlets, identities, have
peers you can talk. It could be friends
as well and then some sort of
understanding and kind of way of taming
your mind if you will or being able to
see that the mind has the life of its
own. That's been helpful for me and I
will say again could happen tonight but
I I haven't touched any prescription
drug for anything sort of mind related
and that toolkit has kind of kept me
head above the water so far for 25 26
years.
>> I have a very left turn question for
you. Hopefully it won't be incredibly
offensive but I was just thinking when
you were like I would knock on wood but
I don't want to make any noise and then
you're like you can let my hair down,
you know, no offense. Sorry. and you're
very polite and I've only been to
Finland once. I was walking around and
of course went to the obligatory saunas
and so on which I actually can tie into
my story. But I was walking around and
in the maybe two days that I was in
Helsinki, I thought to myself cuz I've I
lived in Japan. I speak Japanese. I'm
still close to my host family who I
stayed with when I was 15. And I thought
Finnish people feel like white Japanese
people. That was my feeling there. And
the reason it ties into the sauna,
different context, but if you go to
Japan, it's like everything is is very
restrained. It's very polite. People
don't stare you in the eye when you're
walking down the street. And in Japan
though, if the boss says, "We need to go
out and drink."
When you drink, okay, and if the boss
says you have to drink, you have to
drink. But you go out and you can get
really loud and you can get really
boisterous. You're allowed to say things
when you've had some alcohol that
basically everyone agrees they're going
to forget the next day like it never
happened. Now, [snorts]
I can't take it that far with Finland,
but when I went to the saunas, one thing
that I was very surprised by is that
they sell huge like Stein glasses of
beer that people bring into the saunas.
And I was like, "Oh, this is where they
let their hair down." Okay. Am I totally
off base? I don't know if you've spent
time in Japan, but culturally, I felt
like in my 48 or 72 hours of exposure, I
was like, "Wow, even Finnish itself has
some of like the phone, some of the
sounds of Japanese." I mean, it sounds
like I'm really overreaching now, but am
I just an insane person or do you feel
like there's something possibly there? I
think there's similarities and you're
definitely the connoisseur of a Japanese
culture versus me having just been to
Tokyo and a few other places a couple of
times, but that kind of space and
distance and politeness that people
Well, actually, there's no distance in
Tokyo obviously, but the sort of
emotionally there is a kind of distance
>> Mhm. in Finland and Japan versus
when I came to America 2003, moved to
California, it's like everyone's on your
face and everything's freaking awesome
and it took [laughter] a couple of years
to it's like wait just come on like give
me space and everything's not awesome.
So yeah, maybe there are similarities
and then yeah, alcohol I'm sure has been
a mental health tool not very effective
at that in Finland for many many
decades. But sauna I have to well first
of all there's 5 and a half million
people in Finland and there are more
than 3 million sauners more than 3
million saunas.
>> It's a crazy number.
>> So on average you have one to two people
per sauna in Finland.
Babies used to be delivered in sauna
>> really
>> in Finland because the clean bacteria
dies in a heat
>> sterilized right
>> there warm water I think my mom was
delivered in sauna I was in a hospital
just to be clear so sauna is beyond
being part of the culture it's part of
the DNA and it's culturally it's an
amazing place actually not just kind of
let loose and your hair down but you
don't have your uniform you don't have
your titles you don't have your whatever
social economics signals, symbols, fancy
waters and everyone comes together
whether that's family or your friends or
your community and s is definitely a
place where a lot of things happen in
Finland and we can talk about saers and
its role in a culture but it's something
way beyond cold bars and sauna.
>> Well, let's talk about it. Why is that?
Why is it so prevalent in Finland?
Because it seems like, and I'm sure
you've seen this, but like there are
certain studies in the world of
psychedelics where it's like they did
brain imaging and one study that they've
been slicing over and over again and
torturing the data again and again to
just produce more and more papers on
this one study that was done so long
ago. It seems like the same group of
like 140 fins has been dissected
5 million times in various announcements
around saunas. But why is it so
prevalent there versus other places? I
don't know the origin story.
>> Hopefully there's a historian who will
check me on this, but it definitely goes
back hundreds, let's say, many hundreds
of years where it was sort of necessary.
So, you know, Finland, four seasons,
incredibly cold winters. So, sana was a
place to basically heat and warm up in a
winter. It was also a place where, you
know, you could dehydrate food. That's
kind of how it goes way back when, and
obviously now, you know, it's not
necessary to stay warm and it's not
necessary to dry your food, but I think
that's kind of where it started. And the
initial sound as well kind of duck into
a side of a mountain and then you burn
wood on top of rocks and then you
extinguish the fire and then you make
sure that the smokes goes away and you
know the rocks stay hot for a long time
and you go in. That was the original.
People still have that kind of soundness
today. It's called smoke sauna.
>> Mhm.
>> Essentially you don't have a way to get
the smoke out other than open the door.
So there's no fireplace where the smoke
just goes through a chimney. So that's
called smoke sauna and it's a special
sauna experience and obviously it takes
much more time to heat it and make it
safe and because you don't want to go
there where the smoke but I think that's
kind of the history and then somehow I'm
I'm missing the link how it became sort
of like a culture but now nobody will
build a house without a sound like
literally first is where the sauna and
then let's figure out if there's space
for a bathroom like that's kind of the
order [laughter]
in Finland. I went to this
public sauna.
It's pretty fancy. And there's a word.
You could probably tell me what it is.
It's like lea or something like that.
>> Oh,
>> yeah. There we go. There we go. So, this
is what the act of throwing water on the
stones. Is that what that refers to? Or
the sound that it makes? I don't know
what the name of the actual location
means, but you can tell me in a second.
But the reason I bring it up is I have
never experienced so many varieties of
sauna and they had a smoke sauna room
and in my mind looking at the menu of
options before going in I'm like okay I
get it. It's a hot room. How different
could it be? But the experiences in the
feeling in the body and the way it
penetrates your
sort of being is very different. I was
shocked because I've spent so much time
in dry saunas in the US and I've also
done steam rooms and so on, but I did
not expect there to be such a broad
pallet of experience in saunas. So that
place was amazing.
>> Yeah. So I guess Eskimos have dozen or
so words for snow.
>> Yeah. because they know every nuance and
you know kind of detail and and fins
have dozens of words for different
things around sauna that you can't even
in translate. Lolu is probably the most
important. You judge the sauna and its
quality based on lulu and lolu is
essentially it's after you throw water
into the rocks the fireplace the rocks
and then the steam comes up. It's not
the steam. It's not the heat. It's the I
guess you could say the spirit of the
steam, but how it feels, how it lands.
And let me tell you, there's million
different variations how it happen. Is
it too hot? Is it too kind of sharp? Is
it soft? Does it sort of linger around?
And how does it feel on your body? That
is Lulu. And you judge the quality of
the sound based on a Lulu. And there's a
whole science to it. kind of like how
big is the space to get the loader right
in a barrel sound which by the way I
have at my house is very very hard
because it's too small the fireplace you
can't get high enough and you should be
sitting kind of above the fireplace so
so yeah Lulu is if you know one word
lulu and you want to impress fins you go
to a say what a fantastic Lulu
[laughter]
[snorts]
>> I feel like I need to reach out to the
the Finnish tourism board to sponsor
this episode [laughter]
get people headed over to Finland. I
really enjoyed it. It was a very short
trip, but hopefully I'll I'll have a
chance to get back.
Let's let's talk about metabolic health
because certainly Verta, we can talk
about Vera. And a part of the impetus
for this conversation was tons and tons
of text messages back and forth. And
some of them I'm sure we can't talk
about publicly necessarily because it's
internal data or whatever. But I would
have say a conversation with Dominic
Dagustinino who some long-term listeners
will know synthesizes novel exogenous
meaning supplemental ketones and so on.
And I was, for instance, I'll give one
example, facing a bit of an enigma in my
own experience, which was I've I've gone
into ketosis, and I know that's a very
kind of sloppy way of putting it, but
let's just say getting into ketosis. So,
eating a predominantly fat-based diet or
even doing it through fasting, getting
to a point where I feel like my brain
has switched over to ketones. And I was
lamenting to Dom Dominic that my devices
were telling me I was not in in ketosis.
And I found this implausible because
after so many years of experimenting
with it, I feel like I have a very good
bead on when my cognition clicks over
and is actually operating at a much kind
of faster CPU capacity. But my finger
pricks with say a precision extra device
or the Keto Mojo were telling me I was
basically not ketosis. And very
confusingly, even with a breathbased, I
think it's ketone air or something like
that. Pretty primitive device. But even
with that, I was being given a negative.
and you sent me a text showing your like
bar graph over the last 10 years or
something of measurable ketone levels
going down over time even though
presumably you're increasingly and
increasingly fat adapted and I was like
of course Sami has this data and then
you have some fascinating fascinating
data I have certainly never seen
anywhere else
looking at different cohorts with
various combinations of things with or
without say dietary ketosis. That is
part of the reason I wanted to have you
on. You're such a meticulous thinker
around these things and data cruncher.
But let's let's maybe just define some
terms before we get into things.
What is metabolic health? And maybe you
could tell your personal story because
my understanding is at some point yours,
you know, sub 10% body fat, but your
report card in terms of biomarkers and
so on came back and you're pre-diabetic
is my recollection. But perhaps you
could take that TED talk I just gave and
[laughter] use it as a leaping off point
for discussing defining metabolic health
and then talking about your own personal
journey maybe as a starting point.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And first the the
caveat which is that I I do have two
master's degrees but I'm not a medical
doctor and I don't play one on the
internet and I'm sure in this
conversation we'll kind of go into that
area. So I just want to be clear I'm not
giving medical advice to anyone and I'm
not a medical doctor but obviously have
a lot of experience with the topic that
you just asked. But in terms of I guess
the personal story, so just rewind not
quite all the way back to to Finland,
but again my background is not in
medical field. I'm a physicist by
training and in fact started my career
in a nuclear power plant way back when
in Finland when it was still fashionable
and I guess nuclear power plants coming
back to fashion now now again which is
just to show that my background is in
sort of science and technology not in in
healthcare. However, I've been
essentially an athlete all my life.
Cross country skier bath althlete came
to America, started doing triathlons and
>> Well, you had to ski to school at one
point, right?
>> Yeah. Sounds very idealic. Maybe that
was a punishment by my parents. So,
Nordics came to school indeed.
[laughter] First grade through sixth
>> sounds terrible actually.
>> So quite something. And the biatlon came
handy. So carrying a rifle so I could
shoot the bears when they were attacking
along the way, which may or may not be
true. I was an athlete and have been an
athlete all those years and then after
coming to America started doing
triathlons and a pretty high level
athlete again we're not talking about
Olympic gold medals but as an amateur
and did many many Hawaii iron mans I
think seven of those world championship
races and even won the world
championships in my age group as a
triathlete
2012 I believe and I I give that all as
a background context because my view on
metabolic health and sort of chronic
disease type diabetes and obesity was
this is very embarrassing to admit was
the following which is it's ridiculous.
It's very simple. People know exactly
what to do. Most people, most Americans,
they just don't do it. And as a result,
we have just obese people everywhere.
Everyone has pre-diabetes or type two
diabetes. By the way, it's more than 50%
of American adults. Now, the data is I
think 93% this is the published
peer-reviewed number. 93% of Americans
are metabolically unhealthy in one way
or another. American adults and you know
that's either you have a high blood
pressure or your lipids off or you're
obese or you have type two diabetes or
pre-diabetes. And my view as judgmental
as I was was always listen ridiculous.
You know what to do but you're not doing
it. You're eating too much. You're just
eating too much and you're not
exercising.
you lose her and that's why I pay too
many taxes because healthcare is five
trillion a year of which almost all of
it is metabolic culture related. So that
was my view and I'm very very
embarrassed to say that's how I was
thinking sort of judging people like
you're unhealthy for reasons that are
100% in your control and then like got
the moment where I had to eat a lot of
humble pie and I discovered that despite
you know being
yeah I don't know 10% body fat dicks or
whatever and you know exercising 15
hours a week and performing well as as a
triathlete. I was pre-diabetic. All the
numbers are off and essentially on my
way to type two diabetes. And I was
like, "Shit, wait. I'm not one of those
people with no willpower. I'm not one of
those lazy people. I'm not one of those
quote unquote middle of America 300 lb,
you know, seat belt extender.
That's not me. Seriously, what's going
on here?" And this was 2012, around the
time my previous company, Trulia, went
public. And I was like, well, first I
have to figure this out for myself
because if I can't avoid being
metabolically unhealthy, nobody can.
Well, guess what? Like, nobody can.
Like, that is the status quo in America
today with so many people metabolically
unhealthy. And that got me very
interested in this whole topic of what
is actually driving poor metabolic
health. fortunately met with amazing
scientists who kind of helped me
understand that fundamentally
obesity, type two diabetes, any other
conditions that result from poor
metabolic health, it's not a personal
choice. People don't wake up on a Monday
morning and say, "I want to gain 200 lb
and develop type 2 diabetes. That sounds
awesome. And sticking an insulin needle
to my body for the next 10 years every
day, awesome. Sign me up." No, it is not
lack of willpower. However,
nutrition and food is the number one
driver of poor metabolic health.
>> And if you know how to use nutrition, if
you know how to use nutrition to
actually improve and reverse your
metabolic health,
>> you can take an average, let's just call
it 300 lb middle of America truck driver
or average person that we people on the
coast often look like, oh, it's your
fault. and systematically reverse the
condition nutritionally.
And essentially that's what we've done
at Verta Health now with more than
quarter million patients and you know
scaling fast. But let me just pause
there. That's kind of the how did a
Nordic skier physicist from Finland get
interesting in metabolic health and and
then we can take this down to different
paths. [clears throat]
>> Let's hop in. I want to start with well
as you might expect question about diet.
I want to know what
looking back what the problem was with
your diet and also
this is of course a leading question so
feel free to discard it if it's not a
good question but how large a role does
high fructose corn syrup play broadly in
the US in metabolic dysfunction right if
if that just were removed from the
market what impact would that have but
let's begin with just your personal
retrospective
hindsight 2020.
What was wrong with your diet when you
were exercising 15 hours a week, roughly
10% body fat, performing well in
competition? What was wrong with your
diet?
>> Number one question I get like, oh, was
it your genetics cuz you were exercis so
much? Obviously, genes play a part in
everything, but I just want to remind
that given about 60% of American adults,
6 either have type two diabetes or
pre-diabetes today. Clearly, it's not
like our gene pool has changed. So it
can't really be genes or if 93% American
adults are metabolically unhealthy. It's
not like our genes have changed. So no
it's not that Sami was the n equals one
fin with very very bad genes. This is
happening to a lot of people. So that's
I would say one thing the first one is
there. The second thing is that it is
possible to be skinny and lean and
metabolically unhealthy. some kind of
people of certain background especially
kind of in Asia it's more common that
you don't gain 100 pounds but you're
very metabolically unhealthy
also you can out exercise the calories
and burn and not gain massive amount of
fat but you can still be elevated blood
sugar elevated insulin and be insulin
resistant and that's basically what I
was doing it's very very hard and I can
tell you that I was hungry for 15 years
as an athlete like I'm always more
hungry than I could and if I eat to my
appetite, I'm going to gain fat. I can't
do that as an athlete. So now I'm going
to answer your question. So my N equals
1, I'm absolutely convinced because I
was able to fix and improve it is I was
eating
six meals a day of essentially
incredibly [snorts]
high carbohydrate and incredibly high
glycemic index foods and practically no
fat.
for 10 plus years.
>> So, you weren't eating Twinkies?
>> No,
>> we're talking about rice, things like
white rice, or what are we talking
about?
>> Rice, bread, apples, granola bars, I
don't know, ketchup, pasta.
>> Mhm.
>> But, you know, anything that's has a
glucose molecule turns into blood sugar.
And sure, if it's in an apple or if it's
lots of fiber, it comes very, very
slowly. But if you're eating 4,000
calories a day, of which 3,000 is carbs.
Yeah,
>> do the math. 750 grams of carbs a day or
more. And so you're basically trip
feeding sugar into your veins
constantly. Jamber juice in the
afternoon once I get tired. I just
remember it was my diet all the time.
When you're in your 20s, you can
overdose. People say dose makes the
poison. That's true. you can tolerate
for a long time but once you get to your
30s you know it gets very hard so very
convinced that that was it.
>> What are some of the more surprising
things that you have seen within verta
health now that you have more than n
equals 1?
>> Mhm.
>> And what do the interventions look like?
>> Well let's start from the front end of
of your question. What's the most
surprising? The most surprising is that
we've been able to be successful
with literally anyone. Anyone. And I
I'll give you one example. And and why
is that surprising?
Even overcoming my own concept of it's
all about willpower. I had this like but
it's like people are maybe not as
educated as I am. Maybe they're kind of
busy lives. maybe they don't have my
willpower or kind of the willpower of
willpower Olympians.
>> So that's been one of the most
surprising. We work with Native American
tribes,
you know, 800 or so large employers,
their truck drivers. We've analyzed
outcomes based on what's called ADI, so
area deprivation index. So you take all
zip codes in America and you rank them
by average income
and exactly the same outcomes,
exactly the same outcomes. We looked at
race, ethnicities, exactly the same
outcomes. And these are like large
scale, tens of thousands, hundred
thousands of patients. So that's one
that's been very surprising, which is to
say if you fix the biology,
you fix the outcomes. This isn't, oh,
you didn't even go to high school and
you have a very busy life, so we need
some sort of extra willpower training.
No, you fix the biology, you fix the
body and the outcome. So, that's number
one. Number two is the [clears throat]
magnitude of improvements.
So, to give you a couple of examples,
someone may have had type two diabetes
for 15 years. They are on 100 units of
insulin a day, sticking the insulin
needle three times a day for 10 years.
And we can reverse that kind of state of
type 2 diabetes in 6 to9 months and then
sustain it for long term. 13% average
body weight loss. And this is kind of
like on an intent to treat basis, not
thousand start and then you calculate
results based on five successful ones.
No, you calculate the average results
from all the thousand. So 13%. So in our
clinical trial, that was about 30 pounds
or so.
>> Mhm. average weight loss at one a year
and sustained and mostly fat because we
did dex scans as well. I would say the
third one is the broadsp spectrum
effects and some of these are peer
reviewed. So we've been able to show not
just blood sugar down and reversing type
2 diabetes, not just weight loss, but
we've been able to show up to 75%
reduction in liver disease. It used to
be called fatty liver disease, but
scientists changed it to liver disease
and so it's called mash and massold. By
the way, it's cost hundred billion
dollars a year in America today. There's
one FDA approved drug today. One FDA
approved drug today for MASH. It's one
type of liver disease. It cost 45,000 a
year. [snorts] No kidding. And it came
out to market last year, first time
2025, billion dollars in sales. We
deliver similar results nutritionally.
>> I'm not sure. I think this is public.
This is in our texts. The paper just
accepted through peer review treating
stage four. There is no stage five if
I'm Yeah. I'm remembering correctly,
metastatic pancreatic cancer, right?
This is bad news.
>> This is super super bad news. I mean,
also if my memory serves, this is kind
of like a Steve Jobs type situation.
Okay, but this is treating stage 4
metastic pancreatic cancer with three
chemo drugs. Okay, that's one arm versus
same drugs and on verta, right? Trying
to get patients into ketosis remotely.
And do you want to describe the results
of that? So this was a very well
controlled so randomized control trial
for states for metastatic pancreatic
cancer. We ran the trial with a number
of academic oncology centers. So this
wasn't just us. So very well controlled
randomized control trial.
>> And before I talk about the results just
a reminder pancreatic cancer is number
two or number three killer depending on
the year of cancers in America. So it's
very deadly. It's usually diagnosed kind
of too late. So at stage four metastatic
stage and the life expectancy is usually
sort of 12 to 18 months. It's very very
deadly cancer. And so we had a trial
where we had one arm where we randomized
people. It was chemo three drugs and
then another arm as you mentioned same
drugs exactly same therapy plus the
verda nutrition therapy.
And we were able to show just about 35%
life extension on average in that arm.
So chemo plus verta again it's a very
deadly disease. So 35% is stunning but
of course you know we're still counting
months. It's not that you go from 12
months to 12 years on average. But I
guess going back to your earlier
question that shows the power of
metabolic health and poor metabolic
health and what might be possible like
what is absolutely possible is reversing
type 2 diabetes, losing weight,
preventing liver disease. We didn't even
talk about kidney disease and other
things. But the fact that we can drive
outcomes even with some cancers and I
will say some cancers I can't say like
oh nutrition can cure cancer. M not
quite but poor metabolic health and in
our case we didn't really define the
poor metabolic health in the beginning
but essentially it's high glucose levels
high fasting insulin levels and what you
then might call insulin resistance. Your
body is primary burning sugar and you're
constantly hungry. You're constantly
craving. So even if you're 100 pounds
overweight you're hungry and you want to
eat more of that stuff. That's kind of
the typical state of poor metabolic
health. And then it manifests itself
with type 2 diabetes,
cardiovascular disease,
fatty liver disease, often eventually
chronic kidney disease and and many
other things. And seems like many
cancers thrive in that kind of
environment in that kind of poor
metabolic health.
>> Yeah, I don't think that's
controversial. I mean, maybe look says
the non-d doctor to the non-d doctor,
but I mean certain cancers, not all, are
very glycolytic, right? I mean they're
really dependent on a steady fuel of
sugar to simplify it. Dom I think for
people who want to hear more on that
also Dominic Dugustinino has spoken
about it quite a bit in a couple of my
conversations with him. So what I want
to ask you about because we've teased it
a little bit right the Verda nutrition
therapy. [snorts] I'm looking at the
Verta quick guide right now. If you
don't mind, I'll just kind of lay out
some of it because for me, this is where
probably the magic is embedded and I
want to learn more about how you guys
get the compliance, the adherence that
you do, right? Because that to me has
always been this very elusive,
I don't want to say missing link, but
challenging link with anything
approaching what we might consider a
ketogenic diet. Right? And I want you to
also dispel if I'm making false
equivalence with the ketogenic diet. But
you have curb your carbohydrates, right?
Aim to begin with around 30 g per day
just as needed. And you have some very
important stuff in here, right? Measure
total carbs, not net carbs. This is
where people try sometimes outsmart
themselves. And then you give examples
of what that can look like, right? And
then building your plate. Like what does
an actual meal plate look like? non-
starchy vegetables, moderate protein,
added fat, salt, and extras, etc. I'd
love for you to describe what you have
found to work when you're getting people
started and just what you've picked up
over time in terms of most helpful
components. I was going to say
ingredients, but not food ingredients.
>> Ingredients for for getting people to
>> adhere to these diets because my
assumption, which may be incorrect, is
okay, I Tim Ferrris, I can go to Whole
Foods and buy salmon and vegetables and
this and that. A lot of people in
economically depressed circumstances or
areas or fill in the blank buy a lot of
their what some people would consider
sort of unhealthy food because it's very
inexpensive
>> and it's readily available, right? And
like having spent time around a number
of Native American reservations, it's
like man, there are food deserts in the
United States.
>> What have you found? What have you
learned over the course? Because your
data set is so incredible, right? I
mean, it's just like such a rich and
amazing data set.
What have you learned about helping with
adherence and compliance or modifying
the diet itself?
>> Well, I I will brag because you said we
have big data set. We we absolutely have
the largest data set of metabolic
disease reversal in the world. Like
millions of patient years of data and
data points from each patient every
single day. not just kind of qualitative
information but blood by Marcus. Let me
try to peel the onion [laughter] to
answer your question because a lot goes
into it. So I guess just to take a step
back. Yes, we use nutrition,
individualized nutrition as the core
therapy to treat our patients. It is our
own protocol. I say our own protocol
because any kind of generic label that
you put into it, people go to Google and
they Google and they can go wrong in
1,000 different ways.
>> Mhm.
>> So anyway, so we use our own protocol,
but yes, to address and reverse
insurance, you do have to reduce your
total carbohydrate intake. And we have
those response curves to know that the
more and the better you do it, the
better outcomes you typically see. But
that's sort of number one thing I will
say that yes we use nutrition as a
therapy to reverse metabolic disease and
I will say that as a physicist using
nutrition as a drug or as a therapy is
harder than sort of nuclear physics.
Why? For all the reasons you mentioned
because every person makes a medical
decision three to four times a day.
That's when you eat. It's different
today versus tomorrow and then it's
different between individuals. So it is
a very very hard puzzle to solve.
Unfortunately, you know, computers and
software is is very helpful about that.
So, that's kind of one individualized
nutrition. Number two, so what does it
take and how do we approach key piece
even if you know exactly what somebody
should eat is you kind of need the
support system and I guess that's my
tech background with truly and other
things comes to play that everything we
do we do virtually. So what we can do is
we can monitor your biomarkers remotely.
We give you tools to do that. We can
track blood ketones, blood glucose, your
weight and other things. And then we
have actual real medical doctors, not
me, who are full-time employees who
monitor you and coaches who can who can
then make adjustments.
>> Is that collected through
continuous glucose monitors,
>> connected devices? Yeah.
>> Is it also blood draws or is it mostly
some type of continuous monitoring? It's
all of the above. Some patients get a
CGM and some it's a finger brick, but
not everybody gets a CGM. Depends on the
situation. We do lab draws one to two
times a year. So that's obviously
doesn't can't happen daily.
>> I got it. With the finger prick, that's
some type of Bluetooth enabled thing
that automatically syncs the data. So
they're not manually having to enter any
values.
>> Goes to cloud and gets to us. And I say
that because if you say like, oh, here's
how to eat. Here's a brochure or a book
or something. It's kind of like telling
to a car driver, just hold on to the
steering wheel straight. It's going to
be awesome. And here's brake and gas
pedal. And you know what's going to
happen? The car is going to beautifully
stay on the road until the first corner.
[laughter] It's like, oo, forgot to
mention that we may need to adjust. Turn
left, turn right. And so it's the same
thing with nutrition that unless you
have this kind of a platform, there's
constant adjustments. It's kind of like
a self-driving car. Then if you have the
cameras wide lane and yellow lane or
line and you kind of try to keep it in
between. So with the remote monitoring,
we can kind of try to keep you between
the yellow and and white. So that's the
second thing. The third piece for
adherence and this we start talking
about nutrition.
The most important thing early is to
understand the constraints that a person
has. Now I'll give you silly examples.
If we tell a vegan to have bacon and
eggs for breakfast, you know what
happens? They're gonna say f u c k. I'm
out, right? Yeah.
>> There's no way to convince a vegan to
have bacon and eggs for breakfast. And
vice versa. There's other things.
Obviously, we work with US foods, large
kind of actually food delivery, food
service is truck drivers. Their concept
of a lunch is McDonald's.
>> Mhm.
>> We can't tell them, oh, here's the list.
Go shop Whole Foods. So airon and then
go home and cook at home. It's like,
okay, McDonald's it is. We're going to
reverse your diabetes on McDonald's
diet. And by the way, we do that.
>> Okay. I don't want that to get buried.
>> Yeah.
>> What are some sample meals that people
might get out of McDonald's or something
like that?
>> Perfect. So that's the next step with
food. And maybe I'll give you an
example. It's like, okay, now that we
know you are a truck driver and you will
never become a vegan. You can never
become a vegan. I'm obviously I'm tongue
and cheek here, but most of them don't.
Well, I mean, I'm not a vegan either,
and I'm not sure if you're probably not
either, right? Yeah. As it stands.
>> Yeah. And by the way, we have many, many
successful vegan patients. So,
>> yeah.
>> Sorry if I started a diet war here, but
uh Okay. So, example, your truck. Okay.
So, McDonald's, it's may not be the
pinnacle of health, but we can reverse
your metabolic disease with that. And
let's forget the organics that we'll do
that later if you can. Here's what you
do. You go there, say, "All right, well,
you want your burger. Maybe you even add
extra cheese, but please ask them to
drop the bun and just have like a
lettuce strap. Get that. Then you go to
the condiments. Yeah, mayo might be
fine, but don't take the ketchup cuz
we're going to educate you and tell you
that ketchup is colored sugar.
>> Mhm.
>> You you can't have that. Yeah, you want
your soda. You really want your soda.
Water is not enough. Okay, so go for the
diet coke. Don't take the soda with the
sugar. Again, somebody's listening like,
"Oh, diet coke's bad for you." I totally
agree. I'd rather drink water, but
again, let's not let perfection be the
enemy of progress. So, that would be a
McDonald's kind of a session and off you
go.
>> Yeah.
>> So, that's kind of the second step with
food. And then the third one is is
really empowering the patients
with we talk about AI like AI based
tools. you go to a restaurant or you're
trying to cook something, you can take a
picture and we instantaneously say like,
"Hey, what kind of adjustments should
you make?" And tie that to your actual
situation.
>> Mhm.
>> So, how do you change that? And this
happens every day, two, three, four
times a day. And that's the kind of the
self-driving car analogy that the car
that goes straight is fantastic until
you have a corner. And that's 100% the
diets in America today. So, you can't do
one size fits all. And then before you
ask a follow-up question,
this is mind-blowing for people and ties
to your earlier earlier question as
well. The adherence of verta patients
again which are like real Americans not
sis real Americans
is twice as high at one year as taking a
JB1 drug. M
>> we have 83% adherence retention of
patients at one year and look at any any
of the public available data people
stick to GLP ones like 40% maybe 50%
[clears throat] 30 to 50%.
>> Mhm.
>> Why is that? Number one reason is the
user perceived benefits. It's like I
can't believe I feel this good. I can't
believe I've lost 35 pounds. I can't
believe I don't need to stick the
insulin needle to my body. And the
stories that we hear from people is
like, I'm 65. I thought I don't see my
grandkids grow and I have so much energy
that I'm gardening the first time in 20
years or whatever that is. And you know
this, when you're feeling really, really
bad, you're sick and everything's
hurting and then that suddenly goes
away, that's like life is freaking
awesome. And so I think the number one
reason is the benefits are so strong
versus like a calorie restricted diet
where you're like this sucks but I'm
gonna look good on a beach at least for
a week.
>> How do the experience of benefits differ
from GLP1s, right? Just because we're
segueing directly from that and
certainly a lot of people listening will
either directly themselves have
experienced or know someone who has lost
35 lbs, right? and feels more energy
because the GLP1s do make you slightly
more katotic
>> for the people who are wondering why
they might feel sharper. That's actually
one very plausible piece of the puzzle.
But how do the perceived benefits differ
in a way and maybe there's more to
explain it and I'm sure there is the
sort of two times GLP1 adherence at one
year. I guess that's what you said,
right? So I'm just trying to identify
where those two interventions diverge.
>> First I will say our verd providers
prescribe both oral and injectable GLP1s
when appropriate and or necessary and
when our client the plan sponsor like an
employer health plan have them in a plan
design. So I just wanted to mention that
so that nobody thinks like oh this is
some sort of nutrition dogma. No,
there's effective pharmaceuticals and
especially JB ones in obesity and
metabolic disease context are way better
than the 1980s and '90s diet pills. So
like it's a real real innovation.
>> You guys don't prescribe fanfan to your
patients. Yeah,
>> we don't. We don't. By the way, there
are companies that do that to lower cost
of GLB ones. So absolutely we don't do
that.
>> Yeah,
>> I start from very basics. The GLB ones
100% affect your appetite. So they
change how much you eat. So you eat
less, but they alone don't change what
you eat. So that's a starting point. And
if you don't change what you eat, you're
not going to be perfectly or even
optimally metabolically healthy. And so
one example is
>> you lower appetite, you eat less. But
the second you come off these drugs, all
the data shows that your weight
skyrockets and more likely than not, you
gain fat and you've lost tons of muscle.
By the way, we've shown the patients who
come to us on GLP once and once they
discontinue the drug for whatever
reason, a personal choice or side
effects, we've been able to sustain that
weight loss. This is published and peer
review data 18 months out and soon we
will have even longerterm data, but 18
months no weight regain.
>> Why? Because we start changing what you
eat while you're on the drug
>> and if you do that. But to kind of
sharpen the point to your question,
obviously
we know the side effects of healthy
nutrition. None. Every drug has side
effects. So that's sort of one thing.
And these do ones are tolerated much
better than many, many other drugs. But
there's a lot of things.
>> Nausea and stomach issues. It's
interesting. We've surveyed the patients
who are on GLP1s in our care. 80% of
them say I either want to severely
reduce the dependence on these drugs or
get completely awful. So this idea which
is prevalent at least in the press like
Americans just want to take a pill and
keep taking the pill for the rest of
their lives most people if given the
choice if given the choice to be healthy
without they they don't want to be
taking drugs. So I guess hopefully that
answers the question of what are the
user perceived benefits? Well, there's
no use of side effects when you're
eating healthy food, but with the drug,
you usually have that.
>> I'm not the expert to talk to kind of
how
energy levels or kind of excitement or
mood and things like that change. I
think lots of data will come out when
millions of people on these shelby ones
for years,
>> but eager to see what happens. But
there's definitely a lot of things to be
fully aware like lean body mass in
elderly population 65 and plus people
who lose a lot of weight and shelby once
very kind of alarming reports coming up.
>> Mhm. So, I want to get granular again
with just a hypothetical example of a
vegan, right? Because you mentioned this
this word has come up a couple times.
And in a way, I in my mind, I've always
envisioned that as a tougher nut to
crack than McDonald's just because so
many, how should I put this? This is
true across the board. If you just walk
through any grocery store, including
Whole Foods, there are a lot of junk
foods masquerading as health foods,
which are full of ingredients that are
terrible for you, incredibly high
glycemic, meaning they're going to spike
your blood sugar. Maybe we could talk
about like glycemic index versus
glycemic load, but suffice to say, if
you eat it and you check your blood
sugar, you know, within 90 minutes, it's
going to be a lot higher.
And this seems to be true of a lot of
vegetarian or vegan food also. So what
would be an example of how a diet plan
or let's just say a meal or a day of
meals for a vegan let's just say on the
verta program
>> again I will say everything has to be
individualized but to use kind of
average figures we rarely have to
massively change protein intake for our
patients maybe surprisingly to some
people the standard American diet has a
uh give or take. Maybe it's a little bit
on the low side, but more or less the
right amount of protein.
>> And by the way, that's the most
expensive macronutrient.
>> So sometimes people like, oh, when you
start treating your patients, it must be
so much more expensive. Well, actually,
protein is the most expensive. We rarely
change that a lot. In vegan context,
that's probably the hardest thing to get
right
>> to get sufficient amount of protein. And
you really have to get at least 1.2
grams per kilo kilo. 1 kilo is 2.2 lbs
of protein per lean or kind of normal
body weight. So if you're 80 kilo
person, which is 176 pounds, that would
be a kind of lean person. You kind of
100 g of protein a day is sort of
minimum you have to. So that's probably
the hardest and vegans know this very
well. You have to look at like nuts and
tofu and many to rely on soy and are you
willing to eat eggs, but that would be
one. So we figure out again with the
patient like okay what are you willing
to eat? Are you able to have dairy? You
know some people are okay some not. But
that's probably the hardest usually to
make sure that people get adequate
protein
>> and protein is really essentially it's
the only macronutrient that doesn't
really store itself. So
you kind of have to get it couple of
times two to three times a day to
maintain your body mass. Then after
that, it's actually interesting to get
the sufficient calories.
If there's a lot of crap vegan food,
meaning sugar or, you know, corn flakes
or whatever, then we start replacing
those with healthy fats. And this is
also a miscon, oh, it must be so
expensive because corn is subsidized or
corn syrup is subsidized and then hence
you can have unlimited amount of corn
calories cost nothing. Well, guess what?
You can buy 9,000 9,000 calories. So,
one liter of high quality olive oil from
Costco for like what does it cost? Two
bucks. So, it's a misconception. So, the
cheap subsidized sugar calories
can actually be replaced at the same
cost.
>> Now, if you're very very overweight, you
don't want to be replacing those
calories because guess what? You want
your body to give the the fat calories.
And then around the kind of healthy
vegan food then
we guide the patient towards sort of
leafier less starchy vegetable options.
>> So you can eat very sumptuous vegan food
and I I think we even have you know
because this was a misconception in our
very early days. So we've been pretty
vocal we have bunch of patients who are
vegan. And if somebody Googles fert
health on vegan diet or something,
there's a couple of our patients have
sort of openly shared what they eat,
it's totally manageable. In fact, you
just kind of end up throwing out the
window the crap vegan food. So, I don't
know, sugar frosted cornflakes would be
a perfect example of that or orange
juice or or something like that, which I
love oranges, but orange juice is
essentially soda. Tell me if I'm in
hearing this correctly. So, it sounds
like if you reduce the high glycemic
junk that someone is consuming,
>> you're going to over time improve
metabolic health, right?
>> But is it fair to say that for instance,
the truck driver who's eating the
lettuce wrapped cheeseburgers and
drinking diet coke, like man, you do
that for depending on the size of the
person and blah blah blah blah blah.
Obviously, like if it's a male, I don't
know, maybe in like 3 to 5 days, that
person's probably clocking in at who
knows 0.7 plus mill moles, millimmers,
I'm not sure how you say it, ketones,
right? Beta hydroxybutyrate, I would
imagine. But in the vegan example, maybe
you're simply reducing the glycemic
load, but maybe not getting deeply into
ketosis just because the the question in
my mind was related to the protein,
right? How do you consume tofu, tempeh,
etc., etc., etc., while keeping your
total carb count low? It doesn't
immediately seem possible to me. Unless
they're willing to eat eggs, right? But
if we take eggs off the table, then it
seems like you can significantly improve
metabolic health, but it may not be
through the
vehicle of what would technically be
considered ketogenic. Is that fair to
say?
>> Yeah, that's why we don't really use the
word because again for two main reasons.
One, you Google it and you get your
version that you can either love or hate
and and likely it's wrong. And then two
is it's all on a spectrum or kind of a
dose response curve. And we never want
to let sort of perfection be the enemy
of progress. And
>> the less you have hunger and cravings
and the better you feel, more
sustainable and easier everything is,
including just life. And that's what we
teach to our patients. And you can kind
of be anywhere in the dose response
curve and and be successful. Mhm.
[clears throat]
>> The further you are, we can pretty much
predict not just your health outcomes
year out, but even the healthcare cost
savings, which is sort of insane.
>> Mhm.
>> Cuz drug companies do these trials. You
take one pill, this is what happens.
Take two pills, this and then you kind
of want to optimize where you want to be
on a curve.
>> Mhm.
>> Our therapy is no different. And we show
this to people. We educate. We say this
is your choice and you get here. And but
the beauty is that we empower people so
they can make their choice. And then the
beauty also is that you don't have to be
perfect and you can still be very very
successful. Average diet is so bad
honestly that it's relatively easy to
make early progress.
>> Yeah, the uh standard American diet,
SAD. I just love that [laughter] the
acronym is SAD. It's so good. Whoever
came up with that, God bless you. What a
great acronym. I want to get back to
your training. So, we're going to get
off of Verta [snorts] in a moment, but I
want to say just for people who maybe
have heard the last few conversations
I've had with Dominic, I am deeply
interested in ketosis and the ketogenic
diet and exogenous ketones, but I have
seen
I think Verta is is approaching this the
right way with a greater degree of
flexibility. And I would also just point
to for instance the the slow carb diet
and the 4-hour body. It is not a
ketogenic diet, right? You're consuming
legumes, you're consuming a lot of fiber
in the form of beans or lentils, etc.
>> It is not ketogenic in any way, but it
does reduce or eliminate processed food.
It eliminates most starchy carbohydrates
except for one day a week. And the types
of transformations that you can see
metabolically are just remarkable.
>> Yeah.
>> And granted, you know, that is a book.
So it by nature of its format is a kind
of one size hopefully fits most whereas
Verta is much more adaptable and
customized for the left right turns that
you described.
>> But I wanted to just underscore the fact
that I am not a keto purist by any
stretch of the imagination. And most of
the time I am not in ketosis.
>> Yeah. although I do spend time in that
range. So I want to hop from Verta
to a question around
training. So just in brief, what is and
I'm not sure this number even exists,
but like what is it an average
nonathlete
V2 max? And what is your V2 max?
>> I'm freaking old, by the way. I just
turned Do you know how old I am?
>> I don't know how old you are. You've got
those impeccable Finnish genetics. I
have no idea.
>> Oh my god. I turned 50 in December.
>> Oh, nice. Congratulations.
>> Yeah. So, I'm very very old. This is at
least what my uh
>> that old
>> two kids tell me.
>> Yeah.
>> Who are like 10 or something. But
>> I think at this age in particular or
even like a 30-year-old fit male.
So, V2 max is measured relative to your
body weight. So, it's how much oxygen
you can consume, your body can utilize.
So it's milliliters per kilo per minute.
I think it's maybe 40
>> would be on the average side.
>> 40 maybe or 35 or 40 or 45. My measure
is is more than 80.
>> Mhm.
>> 80 milliliters. This is pretty high.
Very high. Caveat is it was measured
like a couple of years ago. So it's
probably a little bit lower today
because V2 max tends to go a little bit
down as you age. you can still kind of
increase the percentage of that that you
can produce for five or 10 or 15 or 20
minutes. But yeah, it's very very high.
I think the highest ever measured
recently it's more than 100. But if
you're 90, you're kind of 85 to 90 gets
you to Olympic podium in endurance
sports can get and again it is it's
that's not the one and only measure.
There's a lot of other things, but if
you're above 90, you should not be doing
podcast. You should be in the Olympics.
[laughter]
Well, good news, bad news. I'm going to
stick with the podcasting. I am
definitely not above 90. So, the reason
I'm bringing this up is that in
conversations with my doctors and, you
know, people I really trust as well as a
number of podcast guests like Tommy
Wood, Dr. Tommy Wood, who is a
neuroscientist and phenomenal athlete.
Also, the topic of endurance training as
it factors in, I hesitate to use some of
these labels, but endurance/erobic
training as it factors in. You'll see
very quickly why I'm struggling with
terms, factors into health span and
longevity. It's become a topic dour in
the last handful of years in particular.
And the way it's been presented to me
is, and I'm particularly interested in
this for its implications for cognitive
health and potential volutric changes
and the hippocampus and so on with
certain types of training given that I
have Alzheimer's in my family. But the
the way I've been taught to think about
it is that let's just say zone 2 is the
base of the pyramid and then V2 max is
the height of the pyramid. And you're
trying to maximize the total surface
area slash you know size of that
two-dimensional pyramid. And I will
confess it's very I'm very ashamed to
confess I hate sitting on a stationary
bike. I absolutely loathe it. I find it
so boring. And I I also just see these
long-term changes in the sort of
kyphosis, like the hunchback postures of
some long-term cyclists. And I want
nothing to do with that. I have enough
back issues as it is. So my question for
you is when you're trying to get a
normie
to do more endurance like training and I
am on the path I have some spinal issues
with with the lumbar and sacral kind of
segments of the spine which I won't bore
everybody with right now but I'm hoping
to get to a point where I can actually
do sports I enjoy like jiu-jitsu or
other things which at least for
highintensity interval training mimic
something like the Norwegian 4x4 really
well. Right. So, I could do a round of
four minutes, take three minutes off, do
another round of four minutes, and like
maybe it's four minutes on, four minutes
off, or 3 minutes on, 3 minutes off, but
close enough.
>> Mhm.
>> If I'm doing it consistently. But as it
stands right now, I I can't really do
incline treadmill with say a rucks sack
or something for zone 2 because of the
hip extension and the issues that causes
in the lower back. So despite my best
efforts to avoid the stationary bike, I
keep on ending up on this damn
stationary [laughter] bike. And road
biking just scares me too much with the
traffic, say in a place like Austin.
>> Mhm.
>> Everyone I know here who's done road
biking for more than a handful of years
has had some type of accident.
>> Yeah.
>> What would be your advice for someone
who's like trying to get literally back
in the saddle [laughter]
to do some training? How do you think
about
this type of training as it fits into
health span and so on? Because I'm not
intrinsically someone who enjoys this
particular type of training. And I
remember for the 4-hour body, I was in
South Africa at the Sports Science
Institute of South Africa and they did a
muscle biopsy of my thigh, right, my
quadricep, my vastest lateralis, and
they looked at all the enzymes and I
can't imitate a good quality, strong
South African accent. It's pretty good.
It's a great accent but years I can't
even say years that's how you far it out
the South Africans but or the north
English but the uh the point is he came
back and he showed me these charts of
enzymes like citrate synthes which seem
to be correlated to endurance capacity
and basically his his message was ters I
think that was his name he said
basically this flat line is Homer
Simpson and here is your line which is
like infinitely below Homer Simpson so I
don't think I'm very well built for this
stuff. This was a long litany of
complaints, but how would you suggest I
think about this kind of training,
right? Because it seems important. I'm
not sure how to make it more
interesting. I do find the interval
stuff a little more compelling and it
keeps my attention more than the zone 2,
but
it seems like you kind of want to do
both. What are your thoughts? I'm just
turning this into like a therapy
session.
>> Sure. Asking the non-coach a coaching
question. My favorite topic pretending
to be an expert.
>> Yeah. But you've dealt with coaches.
>> I will take it. Yeah. So my approach to
I've had a coach and then I've
essentially 95% of my life I've self
coached myself because I I take it as an
interesting puzzle to try to learn and
then surprise surprise as an
entrepreneur I don't really want to be
told what to do. So
>> ended up self coaching. So based on that
experience and with that caveat
first of all on a high level my approach
basically in everything in business
metabolic health training is kind of
nail the basics less marginal gains than
crazy and yeah I know it's boring and
doesn't sell a lot of supplements and
stuff but it's like nail the basics less
marginal gains than crazy and when you
do that you get sort of that's when you
actually get the 99% of the results and
and for training specifically also
whatever you want to accomplish it's and
you've done a lot of sports and lifting.
The very basics are very simple. It's
progressive overload and specificity. If
you don't have progressive overload,
even if it's just the walking or hiking
or running, you aren't going to get
better. Initially, when you've done
nothing, come off the couch, it's like
very easy progressive overload. It's
like do anything and you get better. And
then the other one is just the sort of
specificity. Like if you want to be a
sprinter, you can't train like a
marathon runner and vice versa. And you
know, if you want to squat a lot, bench
press isn't going to help a lot. So, so
it's literally those principles that I
use. But to give specific advice to you,
what you just said
to get the cardiovascular
stimuli, you obviously have to get your
muscles burning oxygen, using oxygen,
and then burning, you know, bad carbs
and your heart rate up. So, you you need
to do something for that.
>> Mhm. The reason cycling or any kind of a
bike thing is so widely used, it's
doesn't take space and if it's indoors,
it's very safe and it's low impact.
>> It's low impact. So, one thing I would
say for the bike is and Austin has a lot
of good bike stores. Shout out to Melo
Johnny's and others.
>> I have two indoor bikes upstairs. One
was set up by Tech from Melo Johnny's.
So, I've got the bikes.
>> There you go. So, one is bike fit. if
there's someone who's like a PT and a
bike fitter and say, "Hey, I have these
XYZ issues,
fit this bike to specifically work for
me, as much as I hate it, but so that's
one thing where you could like get the
handlebar crazy high or something like
that. Maybe even do a lot of standing."
By the way, those are fun workouts to
kind of, I don't know, do like a 3
minute standing, 3 minute seated, 3
minute standing or whatever. So that
would be sort of one thing to consider
for the bike that you get a fit that's
specifically for your back issues. It
may not be the world's most aerodynamic,
but if it's stationary bike, who cares?
>> So that's one.
>> The other thing, you don't have a lot of
snow around, but I know you occasionally
go to places with snow.
>> Yeah.
>> Nordic skiing and sort of skinning
obviously. Fantastic.
>> Yes.
>> Fantastic.
>> Skinning. I love I love skinning. If I'm
outside, right, I'm not going to get hit
by a car. If I could do skinning every
day, I would. And my back actually loves
it.
>> Yeah.
>> So, yes, I'm 100% behind skinning.
>> And then, of course, often people who
kind of totally destroyed their knees
and hips, it's it's swimming, which I
hate swimming personally as a travel,
well, elements of it are beautiful. You
go under water and it's kind of like
meditation, but more than 20 minutes and
it's like, please give me a break. So,
swimming is another option. I'll take
the swimming over the cycling.
>> Okay.
>> I went and did some swimming yesterday.
So, like I'm I'm up for the swimming.
>> And then if you live in the mountains,
it's very very easy to get sort of zone
one, zone two by just walking even
without extra weight cuz you go up up
and sort of speed walk. And then maybe
the last one I say if if you have the
self-confidence to not feel too
embarrassed is Nordic walking. So Nordic
skiers do summertime. You either walk or
run with them, but you basically have
poles and you go uphill.
>> Mhm.
>> You'll probably get an extra 10 beats,
heartbeat, and kind of a higher level
exercise.
>> So, it's kind of like jogging uphill
with poles.
>> Poles. Poles. Yeah.
>> Obviously, you could just walk and then
use that.
>> I could get into that. I use poles.
>> And then to the sort of V2 max.
So, building a better aerobic engine in
like zone 2 does help your V2 max too.
And then of course if you lower your
body fat, body weight, the kind of
denominator in the calculation improves.
But specifically V2 max training, you
actually get the adaptation pretty
quickly. I don't do it all the time
crazy amount because it can also burn
you out. The two most common ways to
really hit V2 max is either you do sort
of 30 seconds on offs, like you go very
hard and then 30 second easy, but then
essentially you kind of keep hitting the
V2 max oxygen consumption or sort of two
to four minutes all out. They're very
very hard or two to three minutes all
out and then you take three minutes off
and you do that whatever four or five
times. So, those are the most effective,
I would say, and typical ways to
specifically get your V2 max up, but
they can burn you out if you do too many
of those. And and so, like, for me
personally, what I do typically closer
to like a specific event or race, it may
be like three weeks where I do two of
them a week. So, just like six workouts
and then I drop it to, I don't know, one
every two weeks or something. It can
burn out. And the V2 max isn't just
going to infinitely keep going up.
Bad news. And so maybe that's how I
think about find a sport where you can
comfortably and enjoyably do an hour or
so of cardio, whatever that is. And then
this would be my advice, think
strategically when you do your like a V2
block. And that could be just I don't
know 3 weeks or maybe it's two weeks
every quarter or something like that.
And then the maintenance dose. Again,
I'm using dangerous terms here because
who knows what the optimal dose is. But
>> constantly pushing the V2 max. I think
it's just the injury risk. It burns you
out
>> and it's not going to do anything cuz
once you reach your V2 max ceiling, you
kind of are there. So the broader
question I want to ask you about is sort
of what exercise dogma or sacred cows
you have stress tested because I was
looking at this is a blog post that you
wrote this is a while ago and I actually
don't have written down here the title
but it's about hacking your running
speed in four weeks and god I'm tempted
to read this whole thing but I'll just
read some of it right so my total
running time averaged 1 hour 55 minutes
per week. It's a four-step protocol for
four weeks. So, first, and I won't read
all of this, but you know, develop
muscular endurance by running 10 to 15
minutes every day, right? That might
surprise people cuz it's like, hm,
that's more achievable than I would have
expected, right? And you contrast that
with the conventional approach of doing
like a long run once a week and
increasing the distance each week. So,
I'm not going to steal the thunder. We
could comment on this as an example, but
then broadly speaking, just kind of like
unfounded sacred cows because man, there
are so many everywhere. Not just in
exercise, but everywhere. Number two,
build your cardiovascular engine with
all out.
>> I think this is 10 by one minute set
once a week on a treadmill for
regulating effort. And so the total
workout is less than 35 minutes. And you
give links to scientific evidence.
Number three, plyometrics for quick
improvements in running efficiency. Even
highly trained endurance runners seem to
improve their running times in a few
weeks of plyometrics, which is not that
much, right? Roughly five minute routine
three times a week. Three times 12
explosive box jumps, 3 * 12 jumps for
max height, right? Which sometimes
replaced with skipping into a hill. I
don't know what skipping into a hill is.
Maybe you can explain that. And this
approach took 40 seconds or roughly 10%
per mile off my best running speed in 4
weeks leading up to a competition. M
>> typically a 5% improvement per year is a
huge jump. I mean that's kind of
bananas. And then you also added the
note on simultaneously gained about a
pound or two of body weight. So my speed
gain wasn't due to change in body
weight. So this seems to and uh I just
confessed that I hate endurance stuff.
So I'm really waiting into the deep end
of my ignorance pool here, but this
seems to fly in the face of a lot of
conventional recommendations. So, I was
hoping you can speak to anything that I
mentioned,
>> but also just broadly speaking
>> dogma in exercise because there's so
much crap.
>> Yeah.
>> And there's so many things that never
really get stress tested in daily
living, health, wellness, right? This
like you hear all this crap all the time
where it's like you only use 10% of your
brain. That's not true. Like evolution
wouldn't allow that to be the case,
right? Drink eight glasses of water a
day. It's like, well, yeah, it really
kind of depends. I [laughter] mean,
there's so many recommendations you hear
over and over again. So, what have you
uncovered in terms of dogmas?
>> Well, first of all, that particular
like, oh my god, I need to get fast in
running came
I wanted to do a triathlon. This is
already a couple of years, actually just
about 10 years ago, wanted to do a
triathlon and I was training to row
across the Pacific Ocean with my wife in
a robot, which is a whole another
conversation we can have. And I had
stopped kind of running and I was
lifting weights, doing a lot of front
squats. I was weighing 200 pounds and
like right now I'm kind of in a cycling
team, so my weight's like 177 lbs. I was
23 lbs heavier.
>> It's a lot heavier. Yeah.
>> And I was like, whoa, how do I go from
zero to hero in no I want to be the Tim
Ferris of running. Like how do I hack
this? And
>> you don't want to be the Tim Ferris of
running. I can tell you that is my
Achilles heel.
>> So how do I hack this? And in that
approach, I basically I wanted to slice
and dice running performance or at least
the the minimum fancy Silicon Valley
term first principles but like into its
contributing parts like what are the one
or two three things you need to have one
muscular endurance like you can be
cardiovascular fit but go and run
downhill for 30 minutes or even 10
minutes like your legs are noodles you
can't continue running. So you need
minimum dose for muscular endurance so
that your legs don't fall apart. And I
think I was running for like a triathlon
that had a half a marathon. So 13 miles
13.1 miles to to run. So muscular
endurance was one. Then there was the
efficiency you mentioned and so forth.
But anyways to go back to the actual
broader question. Couple of things for
me especially for endurance sports
triathlon and for like a marathon
running and other things. One is like
massive load and volume and you kind of
get more and more tired over like six
weeks, eight weeks, maybe 12 weeks and
then you taper for two or three weeks
and you hope that after your last crazy
week in two or 3 weeks you dig yourself
out of the hole and then you're super
fast on a race day. It's like literally
you're on a knife edge all the time. And
I completely changed that in the last
four, five years I was really competing
in triathon which is I want to be ready
to race almost at the end of every week
meaning progressive overload but stay
vibrant and no matter how hard of a
workout I do say on a Saturday or Sunday
by Wednesday I have to be ready to hit
hard and feel like I can do almost like
my best numbers. Personally, I found
that more effective
avoided any kind of overtraining. So, I
think when you're lifting weights at the
gym, this concept is much easier to
grasp. It's like let's say do you bench
press and for 3 weeks your reps or
weight just keeps going down. Everybody
would like what the f like clearly I'm
not either eating enough or I'm lifting
too often. But endurance athletes do
exactly that. They kind of keep
grinding, grinding, grinding. They get
more tired and they hope they get out of
the hole. So that would be one thing
that
basically training in a way where you
progressive overload you hit your body
but then in sort of 3 to four days you
are back better faster stronger than
ever and then you keep repeating that.
Personally I found that at least for
myself way safer way more objective and
I always knew oh I'm getting stronger.
Oh I'm getting more tired. All right I'm
going to take two days off or maybe I
have a full rest week. So I would say
that's one thing. The second thing,
again, I'm not a running coach or
running expert per se, but especially if
you have an multiport approach.
It's way better to train the
cardiovascular engine on a low impact
machine. So cycling. So if you're like
doing triathlon, I've done more than 10
full distance and fastest was 8 hours 24
minutes, which is pretty fast for an
amateur, especially before all the
aerodynamic gains that people now have
on bikes. So maybe I could take 10 15
minutes off of that. But the 824 is
pretty fast. I run a 256 marathon off
the bike. I think it was yeah 256 2
hours 56 minutes after swim and a bike.
So reasonably fast. But my longest run
to be able to run a marathon in a
triathlon was usually 1 hour 20 minutes
>> which is like I don't know 9 or 10
miles.
>> So just as an example that would be the
second thing. I don't think you need
specificity in that sense. If you need
to build a cardiovascular engine, do it
in a way that doesn't beat your body
down. So like cycling versus running. So
I think that would be one thing. And
then let's leave the nutrition aside.
But that's like a war like how much
should you eat carbs versus this and
should you do carb loading and all that.
Needless to say, I'm
personally a huge believer that as long
as you sort of fuel the work while you
do it, you don't have to gain because
glycogen stores 3 g of water. So if you
have 600 g, let's just say 600 g of
carbs glycogen in your body. So that's
2400 calories. You have another 1,800
gram of water. So it's 2.4 kilos. So
that's five or six pounds. feel like
fully loaded. I haven't found even for
very long distance, you don't need to
gain five or six pounds, if you drip
feed and fuel the actual work, you get
to the same results. Controversial
statement, but that's that's my
experience. I recommend people read the
blog post also.
And since you mentioned it, and we're
we're probably not going to go for
six-hour conversation. I can't not
mention the rowing 2400
plus miles with your wife. I think that
was 43 days plus 43 days 3 hours
something like that which is sounds like
I mean [laughter and snorts] it really
sounds like divorce camp to me and we
could spend another 3 hours just talking
about this insane decision to bro for
that oh yeah I was way more yeah 2750 mi
roughly from California to Hawaii I mean
the flight itself is pretty long from
California to [laughter] Hawaii but my
question is around domestic
peace or
>> violence. Violence
>> or Yeah. minimizing [clears throat]
violence and I was looking at this piece
in USA Today and it says that you had a
written and signed formal document that
not only described how you you would
treat each other in the journey, but
even how you would respond to specific
complaints and gripes. [laughter] So,
it's like the only thing more Sammy than
rowing, you know, almost 3,000 miles is
having this this document. So, I wanted
to hear about this document and if it
was as helpful as you hoped it would be
and also anything else that you guys
figured out in terms of not killing each
other over that period of time being
stuck on a boat. for listeners just the
context is indeed it's 2400 nautical
miles from Monterey California to Hawaii
Wiki Beach the shortest distance but
weather wasn't really our friend so we
ended up doing 2750
nautical miles and I think it was 45
days and 3 hours but who's counting but
so essentially a month and a half
>> almost seven weeks of rowing with my
wife and and completely unsupported I
just want to be clear no helicopters no
follow boats like They weren't like
submarines around us and and helicopters
dropping bon bonss. It was just two of
us. [snorts] Oh, first of all, there's
so many life lessons. And if you team
are fortunate to find a woman of your
life, that that's definitely a way to
test the relationship's longevity.
[laughter]
And if you survive it both and and come
out together and I will say this, we had
been married for four years. We had
known each other for six years. Having
gone through that experience and hopping
off the boat on a platform in on Wiki
Beach and hugging my wife, that still is
the sweetest moment in my life
>> and hugging her and knowing there's only
one person on this planet who knows
exactly what we went through and it's my
freaking wife. And the fact that we got
it through, we got it through together.
No amount of hardship is going to break
this, including having kids. But anyways
certainly was life transforming
experience in many ways. The document it
served two purposes. One in a kind of
preparation phase I maybe mistakenly
wanted to make sure that my wife is 100%
in. I was like this is what it's going
to take. This isn't show up in two weeks
and start rowing. is it's going to be a
halftime job for 6 months to even get
physically ready and kind of train and
know how to jump into survival suit.
It's a halftime job. So part of it the
document was like I'm signing into this.
I'm not going to give up which sounds
like husband is asking wife to do that
but yes that's me. And [snorts] then the
other half was about behaviors on the
boat. And the most important piece of
the document that served us very very
well is the following. Any and every
decision once it's made is water under
the bridge.
>> Mhm.
>> Because we had to make a lot of
decisions around, you know, safety and
navigation and do we go this angle or
that? Lots of decisions every day like
what do we do today? And you would never
know if that was the right decision
because the weather changes and and it's
one thing to do that at home and then
you go to work and you forget it, but
you're basically stuck in a small stinky
box for 45 days. There's unlimited
opportunities to get back to it and kind
of bigger about it. That was incredibly
helpful and served us very well. The one
thing I will say and then you can ask
other questions. We had a lot of time
obviously 45 days 3 hours
we started about 6 7 hours a day. So
there's 18 hours a day to talk, listen,
be together, can't escape, can't go to
the bathroom, can't lock the door, go to
the bedroom, you cannot. And so some of
it was silence, some of it was we had to
fill the airwaves. And we had all kinds
of questions to each other. And one of
the questions my wife had to me was, I
think we were running out of questions.
She said, "Listen, of all our friends,
if it wasn't me, who would you marry?"
[snorts] And oh man,
>> as a diligent engineer, [laughter] I
stepped into that trap and answered it
going through friend by friend landing
on the very specific one. But anyways,
that is a question no married or
unmarried person should ever answer, but
[laughter] I answered and and we
survived.
>> When you were done with your very
thoughtful engineer's response to that
question, how did she respond? And later
was she like, "Yeah, I just wanted to
like I just for whatever reason wanted
to throw a Molotov cocktail into the
boat and see what would happen." I mean,
like what happened afterwards?
>> I remember it vividly sadly. It was I
can't believe that's the last one I
would pick [laughter]
and uh yeah, I had to explain myself out
of it. But yeah, it was a life
transforming trip during which I made
several big life decisions. one of which
we made together which was to to start a
family which also is is a complicated
obviously big decision to have kids and
entering the boat we were both convinced
that life's too good to destroy it with
children and we literally changed our
minds within the hour at the same time
independently which is is quite
something.
>> All right. You decided to start a family
meaning you made the decision to start a
family on the boat or you actually
started trying to have a family on the
boat?
>> Both actually.
So I think we were about 7 or 10 days in
into the trip. It was very very stormy
early and I had had enough kind of
whites space to ruminate about life and
it was like a lightning strike. I still
cannot explain this feeling of like you
know I was in my 30s.
What is there to do? You know I could
start five more companies and I don't
know put my name on the side of a
hospital which I don't want. Like what's
the meaning? Essentially it's
existential crisis. like what can a
human do? What's worthy of the life? And
obviously there's number of things, but
the lightning that hit me was wow, can
you imagine raising a child? That's
incredible. And I turned to my wife and
said, listen, this is kind of weird
because we've talked about this and we
don't want, but I just feel we should
start a family. And her immediate
response was, "Well, I've been thinking
about exactly the same for the last 24
hours.
>> Exactly the same last 24 hours." And
then and there it was, "This is it. It's
going to happen." And my wife happens to
be even more decisive than I am. So, we
had an irritium satellite phone. This is
time way before Starlink, which is
works, but you know, you can send like a
text message barely. and she texted to
her girlfriend who obviously wasn't
drawing uh and said, "Hey, I'm going to
give you some data. Can you start
tracking my ovelation cycles so you can
tell us, text us back when is the exact
timing?" [laughter]
And we sure tried on a boat and I will
say that was the least romantic moment
for both of us. [laughter]
The fun part of this story is this is a
little bit of a mystery, but
we got off the boat just about
10 years and n months ago now and my
oldest daughter is 10 years old.
>> So, there's a little bit of a mystery
what happened and where it happened, but
it's very close.
when you had that lightning strike, you
both
very coincidentally or not had that
lightning strike at roughly the same
time.
If you tried to explain it, do you think
it was just the
incredible
isolation of the two of you? Was it your
wife saying, "Oh my god, I love Sami,
but I need at least one other person to
talk to." [laughter] What what do you
think if you had to try to explain it
even if it's grasping for straws like
what do you think led to that lightning
strike? My guess is
it was the clarity of thought when there
were no distractions
like the clarity of thought and I I
think there's even a theory of the brain
or the mind is kind of basian like you
have prior you have so many priors and
you're always stuck in your rigid
thinking and you know obviously there's
science that you can kind of loosen
those priors with psychedelics and other
things and then you kind of see things
clearly.
I honestly think that there was the
ability to think cleanly and clearly
and that that's kind of what contributed
to it.
>> And what I found in life is ultimately
the human experience is 100% subjective.
>> Mhm.
>> And
outside of that, you know, it's just
computers, right, and algorithms, but
it's 100% subjective. And when you
really tune into the subjective
experience,
often times the biggest decisions in
life are based on that. Like who do you
marry? By the way, I had a spreadsheet
for that too. But then I realized met my
wife. I threw the spreadsheet out the
window and that was it. Same thing about
having children. Like the truly
meaningful decisions, they are
ultimately
subjective in nature. And when you're
truly in kind of touch, how does it
land? How does it feel? the answer kind
of comes there and I I feel in the
middle of the roadboat, no email, no
nothing, no job, no task, no to-dos, all
to space, it was much easier to be in
touch with that kind of experience and
feeling.
>> So that's the story I tell, but uh may
or may not be true. Makes sense to me,
especially after a period of time of
being on the boat, right? Once you have
the routine aspects
more or less on autopilot
>> Mhm.
>> of course you have the decisions about
angle and direction and so on. But I
want to come back to something you said
which was sure I could start five more
companies or have your name on the side
of a hospital. I know as you mentioned
that's not of interest. It seems like
you did not, this is from Forbes, so who
knows, but did not own a car until you
were 36. Talks about basically
how minimalist or some might even say
austere
you have been for certainly a period of
time. And you talk about renting cars
from Thrifty. He had had the cheapest
cars, had not bought a watch in 15
years, exercise clothes are all swag
from various endurance competitions,
which is funny cuz
I sometimes get [__] for wearing all the
free swag that I have. Like most of what
I wear is free stuff that I've gotten.
I've never been accused of having a
great fashion sense. Yeah. And the rest
of his casual wardrobe is 10 copies of
the same t-shirts and jeans. Literally,
this shirt that I have, I basically have
Crew and V-neck. It's the same brand.
It's the same shirt. It's just different
colors. So my question is, is that a
Sami thing? Is it a Finnish thing? And
what are some examples of where you have
found great value in overcoming
that type of frugality where spending
money has actually produced a real
improvement in your quality of life.
People say sacrifice, oh, you have to
say no to so many things. I actually
find saying no and focusing on the
essential incredibly liberating. and
it's kind of my happy place. And so for
some of this like crap around and too
much choice,
what color t-shirt or what kind of
clothes do I put on? I just find it very
liber. I love the fact that things are
as simple as they are. And sure, life is
way more complicated now than say 15
years ago. But I actually like not to
clutter my life with money or anything
else. Let's just put it that way. And
keep things very simple. And I I'll
briefly give the example of the car
story. So yes, I've had my driver
license ever since it was possible in
Finland. It was 18. So 18. But I
actually I didn't buy my first car. My
wife bought it. Maybe I was 36 forced
cuz I had been renting thrifty
car from San Francisco airport for you
know 8 years. Why that is a funny story
but illustrates my point. Well, first of
all, I didn't have any credit in America
and I needed a car after I came out of
Stanford for work reasons. I could go to
Thrifty and rent it. This was like 19
bucks a day. No credit. I could rent it.
And then I realized this is amazing cuz
I travel so much for work. I don't need
to wash the car. I don't need to change
the oils. It got broken into twice in
San Francisco. I could just drive the 19
bucks a day car to airport and drive out
with a new car. I was like, "This is so
convenient. No worries. Ford Escape.
That was my car of choice." And then one
weekend I came home years years later
and my wife's like, "This is it. You
need to own a car. You're an adult. You
can't be renting all the time." And she
bought me the same Ford Escape that I
had been renting for like seven years.
So that was it.
>> So that's kind of where it's I think
mainly coming from that sort of
simplicity and convenience. Focus on the
things that matter. Sure, I have fancy
bicycles to ride fast, but no cars.
>> What was the color? I want to know if
you threw some flourish in there. Was it
white or black or was it like electric
blue with a racing stripe?
>> Unfortunately, it didn't have flames on
the side, but if it was blue, the one
that she bought me.
>> Oh, look at that. I got it.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it was wonderful.
>> No spoiler on the back.
>> No, no spoiler on the back.
>> Yeah. So, my approach to money is very,
very simple. The less I have to think
about, the happier I am. And the fact
that earlier success have enough for
house and food and leftovers is
wonderful. But if I have to be thinking
about the leftovers at all, something's
wrong. So it's just simplicity is very
very buying time is very helpful.
There's some things that just it's good
to have kind of service and helpers
around. I would say that's a good
investment. And then the one and only
thing where I would say
yeah I I do like sort of living
environment to to have a house that you
can enjoy not for the sake of it but to
have the kind of little things and
conveniences you have whether that's to
be able to exercise
or you know roll into a lake from
>> have a pond to jump into.
>> So I would say that but uh
>> yeah the less I have to think about
money happier I am. It's just focus on
life. Life's happening. Forget the
money. Life's happening. Go and make it
happen.
>> Do you have any books that you recommend
or gift to people more than others?
>> I am not a big book gifter other than
recommend for my like Vera team and
sadly they are like professionally and
they are all too kind of well known and
common that they would add a lot of
value. There's the
>> well what are they?
>> The score will take care of itself. the
49ers coaches Walshshire's book and high
upput management actually the high
growth handbook by El Gilvitz is much
much much newer and I know you've
interviewed El professional setting I I
do read a lot if you want to block for a
book that I've really really enjoyed
over the last year inspiring
very inspiring shows what's possible in
life and a little bit of
leaves this kind of universe leaves you
wondering like what's really true in a
universe and what not is Tjo by Danny
Tjo.
>> No kidding.
>> Absolutely mind-blowing book. You know
who Danny Tjo is?
>> Yeah. Machete. He's appeared in a bunch
of Robert Rodriguez films. Roberts right
here.
>> Oh my god.
>> In Austin.
>> That story, that book.
>> How on earth did you end up picking up
that book?
>> In our family, I read a lot, but there's
one person who reads more. That's my
wife. So, I'd say half of my book
recommendations come from her because
she screens 10 books for everyone that I
read. So, it's a good filter. [laughter]
I cried several times. I laughed several
times and I was incredibly inspired and
came out reading that book, Belief in
Humanity, and and just it was amazing.
So,
>> if you had given me a a million guesses
for what you were going to say, I never
[laughter] would have guessed. Treyjo by
Danny Tjo. It's a t r e j o, right?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Wow. Okay. You're you're full of
surprises, Sami. I like it.
>> Also, if if you are ever contemplating
having a family, that book also gives
humility as you think about how much can
you affect your kids kids's life. And
I'm not going to give a spoiler alert,
but uh it's highly recommend.
>> I'll get it on Kindle today. I mean, we
have covered a lot. I have a few
questions I'd love to ask as we start to
wind down, but is is there anything else
that you would like to cover, make sure
that we
discuss or
anywhere you'd like to point my
audience. I mean, I'm going to link to
everything in the show notes. Of course,
they can find Verta Health Viralth.com
on the website and we'll we'll include
everything where people can find it
easily. But is there anything else that
you would like us to cover? I think you
cover things very very well. I I would
say my professional duty is to be an
evangelizer and say this very sad
metabolic health mess that we find
ourselves in America and globally and
this savvy the common sense thing that
oh the diseases that we talked about
type two diabetes obesity cardiovascular
dis they are chronic and progressive and
the best we can do is to manage them
with an everinccreasing load of
medications is fundamentally not true
and whether that's ver or something else
I I just want be very clear that there's
hope in the horizon and the hope is
largely in in the form of nutrition but
not in a traditional way that you need
to restrict and and suffer. So that's
sort of my professional duty to bring
hope and say if you're living with type
two diabetes and by the way people who
are living with type two diabetes
usually their family members their
relatives and you've seen people lose
eyes and lymphs and lives because of
type two diabetes to me mostly
completely unnecessarily for the last
three four decades that that disease
among with other metabolic health
conditions is fundamentally reversible
and you don't hear that from your doctor
today sadly and it's not doctor's fault
they're well meaning but you go to
medical school, you get literally zero
0.5 hours of nutrition training and
nobody tells that conditions like type 2
diabetes can be reversed like
systematically, not miraculously. And so
hopefully I can be a messenger of hope
that these conditions are reversible,
especially after I already disclosed
that I used to live thinking it's your
fault, it's your fault, you're just
lazy, you don't have a willpower. But
that's not true. Nobody gets these
things because they're lazy or they
decide it's because of our food
environment. And the food environment
kind of slowly but surely poisons us.
But if you know a few little tricks and
changes, you can actually turn back the
clock. So that that's my PSA.
>> Who are the actual customers of Fer
Health, right? Like who should actually
go check out the website?
>> Anyone who pays healthare costs in
America could be and should be our
customer. If you pay healthare cost, you
are paying for the party of people
staying sick and others profiting from
the sickness. So this includes
self-insured employers and we work with
like 800 of them. So essentially all
Fortune 10,000 employers self-insure and
thousands others. So all self-insured
employers obviously health insurance
companies when they take risk on their
patients and this includes the private
Medicare advantage, private Medicaid,
managed Medicaid organizations, state
employee groups, I think we work with 13
out of 50 states today already. So state
employee groups and then some government
entities. There's VA, there's DoD and
others. So anyone who pays any payer who
pays healthcare costs could be our
customer and our pitch to them is guess
what we'll help you make money. Yes
indeed we'll help you make money and a
side benefit is we also save lives.
And I say that because the love language
of American capitalism is dollars. And
so when you can help someone else to
make money you're going to be very very
successful. And I love it. Verta has
done something that I wasn't sure could
be done. I mean that you have as you
already mentioned I mean the world's
largest data set of this type of
metabolic health and disease reversal
and the way that you've been able to
refine and engineer and iterate and
further polish a program for
individualized care and
sort of masscale adherence. It's
mindboggling to me. like it's really
really incredibly impressive. And I
don't want to say I I know how much work
goes into it, but I I think I have an
idea of just how challenging that is
because I think of myself as someone who
kind of specializes in behavioral
change. And to your point,
you can do a lot of really innovative
things once you free yourself from the
tyranny of the perfect, right? Not
letting perfection be the enemy of
progress. That is the mistake of a
one-sizefits-all approach. Like you need
to be on the ketogenic diet and you need
to hit this minimal concentration of
blood blah blah blah blah blah. It's
just not going to work on a mass scale.
It just doesn't work. But when you have
different ways to help people improve 5,
10, 20%, 50%. M
>> the way that moves the needle over time.
This is not the right way to put it, but
it defies it defies conventional
explanation
in the way that as you already put it, a
lot of doctors have been taught in their
minimal exposure to say nutrition,
right? So the science that you're doing
and I'll say it right as it's on me but
like really what you're doing with the
controls and with the trials but also
with the cohort analysis and everything
else you're doing internally like the
science you're doing is incredibly
incredibly valuable and I don't just
mean that in dollar science. It's
valuable to humanity.
So, I really applaud you for
building
Verta and I just felt like we needed to
have this conversation because a you're
just such a freak of nature and I wanted
to talk to you about all [laughter]
all the things we've talked about, but
also because what you've built is
something that I I wasn't sure it could
be built.
and with the many text messages and
seeing a lot of stuff that just blew my
mind, I wanted to have you on. So, I'm
glad and grateful that you took the
time.
>> Yeah. Thank you so much. And honestly,
appreciate those kind words. It's 11
years in the making and never take it
for granted. Bigger company, bigger
problems, but uh [laughter]
trying hard every day.
Well, I'm going to pick up Trey Hall,
which is not what I expected to be my
immediate next step after having this
conversation. But for everybody
listening, we will link to everything in
the show notes. You can find Sami.
Certainly, you can find Verta first and
foremost at vertaalth.com. Vir TA. You
can find Sami Incan. Good luck with the
spelling. s a m i n k i n on
[clears throat] all of the places
samienan.com
on Instagram x etc. I'm not sure how
active you are on those but check out
the blog posts for sure and we'll link
to everything as I mentioned in the show
notes at tim.blog/mpodcast.
Just search for Sami Sami. I can promise
you he's the only one who's going to pop
up. [snorts] And until next time, just
be a bit kinder than is necessary
to others, but also to yourself. And
take those 20 minutes on Sunday. Plan it
out. Get those things in the calendar.
Otherwise, it's going to get crowded out
by the universe. And then woe is you,
woe is us. So, take care of that. And uh
Sami again, thank you so much for the
time.
>> Thank you very much.
>> All right, folks. Until next time,
thanks for tuning in.